Finding Aid for Elizabeth Green papers, 1928-1993
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Elizabeth Green papers 1928-1993, 1950-1988
Green, Elizabeth A. H.
3 linear feet
97115 Aa 2
Professor of music at the University of Michigan School of Music. Green was a noted writer and teacher on the topic of teaching violin and other string instruments. Correspondence, biographical information, lectures and various writings, course materials, programs, and subject files relating in part to Nicolai Malko and Ivan Galamian; also photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated in three accessions: in January 1996 by Assistant Prof. Stephen Shipp, and in June 1996 and March 1999 from Green's cousin, Becky Hunter (Donor no. 8447 )
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Elizabeth Green was born in 1906 in Mobile, Alabama. She attended Wheaton College, graduating in 1928 with a degree in music. Her specialty in the years ahead would be stringed instruments, especially the violin. After college she then became a high school orchestra teacher in Waterloo, Iowa, a position she held until hired by the University of Michigan in 1942. While in Iowa, Green also served as concertmaster of the Waterloo Symphony Orchestra from 1935 to 1941. In 1939 she received a master's degree in Music from Northwestern University. After coming to Ann Arbor, Green was also named to the staff of the Ann Arbor public schools as a teacher of stringed instruments and orchestra director, positions she held until 1962. In 1948, she was promoted to assistant professor at the University of Michigan School of Music. In 1963 she became a full professor. She retired from teaching in 1975.
Elizabeth Green wrote extensively on the topic of violin instruction. She wrote for such periodicals as the School Musician in the 1930s, The Etude in the 1940s and 1950s, The Instrumentalist in the 1950s, The Music Journal in the 1950s and early 1960s, and The Music Educator's Journal throughout the 1940s and 1950s. In 1961, her third book, entitled the Modern Conductor, was published by Prentice-Hall Press. She continued writing numerous books including a collaboration with the famed Russian violin teacher Nicolai Malko. During the period of the 1960s, Green began a longtime friendship with Ivan Galamian (she was a student of his during the summers from 1947 to 1952) and his wife Bertha. Some of Green's other works written while she taught at the University of Michigan included The Conductor and his Score (1975) and Teaching String Instruments (1966). She also published several pieces of music including Hohmann for the String Class (1949) and 12 Modern Etudes for the Advanced Violinist (1964).
Though she retired from teaching in 1975, Green maintained an active lifestyle. In 1971 and 1983 she served as a judge at the Nicolai Malko conducting competition. In the 1980s she gave lectures and conducting clinics. She also continued writing; her book The Dynamic Orchestra was published in 1986. In 1993, she neared completion of a biography of her friend and fellow music teacher Ivan Galamian. Written when she was 85 years of age, Miraculous Teacher: Ivan Galamian and the Meadowmount Experience, was to be her last work. She passed away on September 24, 1995.
The Green collection consists of three linear feet of material arranged mainly alphabetically by type of material or topic. The materials focus on her years as a teacher both in Michigan and Iowa. Green devoted her life and career to the teaching of proper methods for teaching stringed instruments to students at all levels of instruction from elementary to college. She was also a prolific writer of articles about violin instruction, some of which generated a significant amount of comment. Of particular note in this respect is her January 1941 article in The School Musician. This article concerned her belief that band groups and classes were being favored by parents and band directors at the expense of orchestral groups and classes. The article and responses she received are included in the collection.
Other strengths of the collection include numerous articles that she wrote or which were written about her. There are samples of her course syllabi as well as other materials relating to how she conducted her classes. The largest part of the collection includes her correspondence with friends, family, fellow educators, and her students. The materials in the collection cover the length of her career as a teacher and instructor at the University of Michigan as well as the lectures and clinics she conducted during her retirement years. The collection contains very little about her youth, but there are a few newspaper articles about her father, Albert W. Green who was a violin maker and instructor. In addition there is an audio recording of a lecture she gave September 20, 1978 at the University of Connecticut. The photos are mainly of Elizabeth Green herself. The ads and reviews mainly pertain to her 1961 book The Modern Conductor, but there are also ads from some of her other works. There is a complete copy of her 1966-1967 manuscript Teaching Theory Creatively.
Subjects:
Green, Elizabeth A. H.; Galamian, Ivan.; Malko, Nicolai, 1883-1961.; Violin--Instruction and study.; University of Michigan. School of Music.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Personal materials
  (arranged alphabetically)
  - Ads/Reviews 1960-1987 (Box 1)
  - Articles and Clippings by and About Elizabeth Green 1940s-1980s (Box 1)
  - Audio Recording:, 7 1/2 ips, stereo, four track (Box 1)
    (Side One: Lecture Given September 20, 1978 at University of Connecticut; Side Two: Lesson Given To Conducting Class)
  - Class Notes--Band Technique Summer 1937 (Box 1)
  - Conducting Clinics 1981-1986 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - 1928-1959 (Box 1)
    - 1960-1964 (Box 1)
    - 1965-1969 (Box 1)
    - 1970-1979 (Box 1)
    - 1980-1988 Undated (Box 1)
    - 1992, Galamian Book Research and Citations (Box 1)
    - 1992-1993, Galamian Book Research and Citations (Box 1)
    - 1960-1988, Prentice Hall Press (Box 1)
  - Course Syllabi Undated (Box 1)
  - Curriculum Vitae (through 1966) (Box 1)
  - Kitchener, Ontario, Canada Lectures 1988 (Box 1)
  - Lectures, Open Letters, and Other Non-Published Writings 1947, 1951, 1958, 1960, 1995, undated (Box 1)
  - Malko, Nicolai 1941, circa 1960-1971 (Box 1)
    (Materials about him from 1941 and 1971 plus information about the Malko Conducting Competition, 1960s and 1970s)
  - Materials by and about Albert W. Green (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Materials from a Scrapbook 1941 (Box 1)
  - Music Written for Elizabeth Green and Other Honors Received (Box 1)
  - Nicolai Malko Competition: 1971, 1983 (Box 1)
  - Photographs (Box 1)
    (include portraits of Green and Isaac Stern)
  - Recital and Conference Programs 1940s-1980s (Box 1)
  - Teaching Theory Creatively Manuscript 1966-1967 (Box 1)
  - University of Illinois Lectures 1986 (Box 1)
- Biographical
  - Biographical information 1932-1988 (Box 2)
  - Honor certificates 1940-1978 (Box 2)
  - Personal correspondence 1971-1995 (Box 2)
  - Personal correspondence with students 1969-1989 (Box 2)
  - Political activity (Box 2)
  - Press notices 1953-1985 (Box 2)
  - Sheet music, Inscribed 1962-1981 (Box 2)
- Teaching
  - Clinics and workshops, Correspondence and details 1941-1995 (Box 2)
  - Conducting 1967-1988 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence with former students 1970-1989 (Box 2)
  - Former students, Recommendations 1968-1990 (Box 2)
  - Lecture notes 1969-1994 (Box 2)
  - Lesson plans (Box 2)
  - Midwest Music Conference 1988 (Box 2)
  - Photographs (Box 2)
  - Requests for instruction 1983-1986 (Box 2)
  - Sheet music 1967 (Box 2)
  - Teaching stringed instruments in class 1950-1988 (Box 2)
- Publications
  - The Conductor's Score 1972-1985 (Box 2)
  - The Dynamic Orchestra 1985-1990 (Box 2)
  - The Modern Conductor 1967-1990 (Box 2)
  - The Modern Conductor, Workbook 1982 (Box 2)
  - Music and the Mind of Man 1987 (Box 2)
  - Musicianship and Repertoire 1967-1968 (Box 2)
  - Orchestral Bowing 1968 (Box 2)
  - Principles of Violin Playing and Teaching (Galamian) 1969-1984 (Box 2)
  - Reviews 1981-1991 (Box 2)
  - Sonata from an Easter Cantata 1982 (Box 2)
  - Twenty-six Days in the Soviet Union 1959 (Box 2)
  - Unpublished 1982 (Box 2)
- Competitions
  - Judging competitions (Box 2)
  - Malko Competition
    - 1974 (Box 2)
    - 1979-1980 (Box 2)
    - 1983 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence 1962-1984 (Box 2)
  - Malko the man 1940-1968 (Box 2)
  - Other competitions 1981-1984 (Box 2)
- Other interests
  - Ann Arbor Chamber Orchestra 1980 (Box 2)
  - Art quotations 1977-1987 (Box 2)
  - The brain 1958-1989 (Box 2)
  - Sabbatical 1964-1978 (Box 2)
  - Tourte bow and Montagna violin 1948-1990 (Box 2)
- Other materials
  - Photographs (Box 2)
  - Unprocessed (Box 3)